Guide to the Ralph Mayer Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ralph Mayer papers
1870-1991
MS 1710
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
16.5
(36 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, research and professional files, and photographs documenting the life and career of Ralph Mayer, particularly his work on paint technology.
Mayer, Ralph, 1895-1979
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University School of Art, 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
The computer files are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu. The request should outline the scope and purpose of the research project, why the researcher believes the material is relevant to their project, and contact information. If possible the request should also include a list of specific material of interest including collection, box, and folder numbers (or folder descriptions if folders are not numbered). The review may take several weeks.
Biographical / Historical
Ralph Mayer, artist and authority on paint technology, was born in 1896 in New York. He was educated at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute as a chemical engineer and subsequently became a painter. He studied materials used by artists and in 1940 published The Artist's Handbook of Materials and Techniques. He taught courses in painting materials and techniques at Columbia, the New School for Social Research, and the Art Students League. Mayer exhibited his work and was a consultant in the conservation of paintings to museums and private collectors. Along with his wife, artist Bena Frank Mayer, he founded the Artists Technical Research Institute in 1959. The Institute provided artists with technical information on materials and methods. After his death, his wife reestablished the institute at Yale University as the Ralph Mayer Learning Center. Mayer and his wife were married in 1927. He died on August 3, 1979.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, research and professional files, and photographs documenting the life and career of Ralph Mayer, particularly his work on paint technology.
Arrangement
The material is arranged in seven groupings: research and professional files; teaching and lecturing files; Artists' Technical Research Institute files; writings; correspondence; personal papers; and photographs.
Artists' materials; Painting; Artists; Mayer, Ralph, 1895-1979; Mayer, Bena Frank, 1898-1991
- Research and professional files, 1906-1991
  - Acrylics, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A History of Namta, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American antiques, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Artist article draft and files, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Institute for Conservation, 1967-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM) notes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Society of Contemporary Artists (ASCA) exhibition, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Society of Contemporary Artists (ASCA) pamphlets, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Army-Navy Aeronautical Specification, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Art from Life to Life, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Art hazards project, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Art institutions, 1933-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Artists' Equity Association commendation at luncheon, 1976-05 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Artist's Handbook reviews and files, 1951-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Artist's Handbook update, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Art journal, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Art magazines, 1933-1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Art: potential health hazards of fine artists, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Assignment to Viking Press, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - A volume 1 number 1 photograph notes, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bijutsu Shuppan Sha, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Board, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Book information, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Book 3, including letter from Manuel Komroff about new book with Dr. Toch, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Book 3, return to Mayer, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Booklets, general, 1961-1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Booklets, Columbia University and the American Chemists Institute, 1962-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bressler's Restorers, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Catalogue of Portraits and Sculpture of the Chamber of Commerce, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chanel, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Color, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Colors price list, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Conference, Oberlin, Ohio, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Conservation
    - 1970-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Circa 1906-1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Materials by others - publications and correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Copies of American Art Award notice, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Copies of reports of work accomplished, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Deutsch Gallery, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dictionary reviews, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Duplicates of Gleuck, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Early silver pamphlets, 1946-1970 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Early statements and mixed useful reports, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Egg tempera
    - General, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Gouche and water color (Columbia), results, and 101-102 projects, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Manual, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - English pamphlets, 1946-1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Epoch making items, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Excerpts on hazardous materials, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition fliers, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Experiments in Art and Technology, Incorporated (EAT), 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Extra sheets - old foundation, University of Delaware, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Felt tip reports, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gesso, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Graphic arts, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Guggenheim grant certificate, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Historic materials, 1925-1940 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Industrial paint instruction, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Inventions, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Inventories, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Japan: bill for colors and article by Japanese friend, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Juries, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lacquers report, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Lighting, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Literary agents, 1970-1991 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Material for archives, 1961-1985 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Materials and equipment, 1941-1966 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Materials of art and archaeology, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Materials regarding The Artist's Handbook, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Materials regarding exhibition, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Materials regarding exhibition, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Materials regarding Sidney B. Levinson, 1960-1966 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Materials relating to laboratory testing, 1962-1969 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Mayer's mediums, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mediums, general, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mediums, varnish, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous files
    - Articles, 1950-1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Magazines, 1942-1962 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - Mentions in booklets, 1949-1970 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Notes on unidentified subjects
      - 1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - 1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Circa 1906-1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Notes and photocopies on unidentified subjects, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Pamphlets, 1960-1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Pamphlets, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Projects, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Publications, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Reports, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Writings, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Mural, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Museum bulletins, 1934, 1944; 1944 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - M varnish, circa 1962 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Nassau Community College exhibition, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - National Conservation Advisory Council reports, 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - New Jersey: A Guide to Its Present and Past, 1953 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - New School Associates exhibition, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - New York Review of Books article with painting, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Nineteenth century canvas dates - United States, outside New York, and foreign, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Nineteenth century canvas makers in New York, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, 1935-1936 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Notes
    - Colors and dyes, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Columbia School of Painting and Sculpture, 1958-1961 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Dermatology, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - M varnish, photocopies, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Research for unidentified writings, 1969-1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Serigraph, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Varnish and conservation, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Wood treatment, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Notices
    - Art show, 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Exhibition, 1965-1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Number 2, 1969-1974 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Write-ups, general (dictionary), 1968-1984 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Oil, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Oils for oil colors, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Original clippings of Maximilian Toch on Rembrandt, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Paint chips, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Paint formulas, industrial, 1921-1952 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Painting
    - In collections, 1966-1978 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Materials, 1949-1969 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Techniques, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Techniques number 2, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Paper
    - 1971-1981 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - 1978-1981 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - 1980 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Pastel, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Phony toxicity and good toxicity (Maximilian Toch), 1925, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Photocopies of notes, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Photocopies of notes, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Pigments, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Publications, 1938-1972 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Publicity - litter, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Purpose, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ralph Mayer long-hand writing for laboratory use, 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Ralph Mayer's Spanish book publishing files, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Recipes
    - Adhesives, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Aqueous paints, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Cleansers, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Compounds, et cetera, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Duplicates (corrected pages), Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Encaustic, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Framing, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - General, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Gouache, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Grounds, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Mediums, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Notes, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Oil paints, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Paint samples (gouache), Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Pastels, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Sculptor's, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Selected industrial, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Varnishes, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Return of loaned paintings, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Revision number 4 - bibliography, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Rubber, 1919-1920 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Sculpture house pamphlets, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Silver, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Silvering mirrors, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Simple book, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Spoon drawings, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Standard, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Stencils of company labels, photocopies, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Subway, temporary, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Survey of portraits at Columbia University, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Syn. org. pigments given to University of Delaware, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The Cody Mural: A Pictorial History of Mormonism, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - The Institute of Art Technology, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - The Techniques of Painting, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - To be typed - for fifth edition, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Toch Brothers, 1924 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Toch Brothers New York book, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Toxic materials, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Toxic materials: direct reference by Ralph Mayer, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Toxicity - handwritten notes by Ralph Mayer, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Transparencies, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Two fliers and the Furniture Warehouseman, 1941-1974 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - United States of America versus Greene, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Useful pamphlets, Circa 1906-1991 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Viking agreement, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Water colors, circa 1951 (Box 9, Folder 22-23)
  - Yale exhibition - Bena Mayer, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Teaching and lecturing files, 1930-1981
  - American Association of Museums lecture - New Orleans, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Binder notes, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Board of Education (George Raye) television talk, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Class - introductory lectures, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Columbia University
    - Columbia Art Program bulletins, 1943-1960 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - General, Circa 1930-1981 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Lecture notes, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Teaching, 1957-1961 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - FAECT: lectures on industrial paint technology, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Gouache, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Lectures, courses, and notes, 1930-1961 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Lectures - exam, 1947-1958 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Lectures, symposia, and papers, 1965-1968 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous course papers, Circa 1930-1981 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - New School bulletins, 1943-1956 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - New School for Social Research, 1957-1981 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Parsons, 1951-1955 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Silvermine College of Art, 1951-1961 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Artists' Technical Research Institute files, 1953-1984
  - Acknowledgment of inquiry, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Appeals for funds, 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Applications for grants, 1968-1984 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Assurance of compliance, 1959-1960 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Establishment materials, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Financial materials, 1960-1967 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - General (preceding Delaware), 1981-1983 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Incorporation materials, 1954-1961 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Journal planning, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - List of organizations receiving funding from the New York State Council on the Arts (NYSCA), 1971 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Logo, Circa 1953-1984 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Materials regarding fundraising, 1969-1971 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 1969-1972 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Museum heads and grant letters, 1953-1979 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - National Endowment for the Arts
    - 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 15-16)
    - 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - 1976 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Applications, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - National Foundation grant (pre-Delaware), 1961-1970 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - New York State Council on the Arts (NYSCA)
    - Fundraising, 1969-1971 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - General, 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 22, Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Note, 1965 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Research to be done, 1963-1971 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Slides of historical art, Circa 1953-1984 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Stamp, Circa 1953-1984 (Box 34, Folder 5)
- Writings, 1932-1984
  - American Artist clippings, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - American Institute for Conservation, 1969-1975 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Article on portrait painting, Circa 1932-1984 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Behavior of pigments in paints, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Book jackets, Circa 1932-1984 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Book order forms and jacket, Circa 1932-1984 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Book reviews of The Painter's Craft and review by Mayer of Jacques Maroger's book, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - General writings, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - General writings, Circa 1932-1984 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Enameling, including writings by Ralph Mayer, 1932-1953 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Publications, 1957-1959 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Writings, 1963-1974 (Box 12, Folder 12, Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Review of Nordmark's book by Ralph Mayer, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Storage Warehouse: originals, Circa 1932-1984 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Technical question and answer page, Circa 1932-1984 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Technical Studies in the Field of the Fine Arts, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - The Artist's Handbook of Materials and Techniques
    - 1937-1981 (Box 13, Folder 6-8)
    - Drafts, 7 (Box 31)
      Conditions Governing Access
      The computer files are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu. The request should outline the scope and purpose of the research project, why the researcher believes the material is relevant to their project, and contact information. If possible the request should also include a list of specific material of interest including collection, box, and folder numbers (or folder descriptions if folders are not numbered). The review may take several weeks.
      - Disk #1 Viking Penguin Inc. 3391 Penguin 1 PEN 01-09.DAT, 1996-m-0120-0001; 1 (Box 31)
      - Disk #2 Viking Penguin Inc. 3391 Penguin 2, 1996-m-0120-0002; 1 (Box 31)
      - Disk #3 Viking Penguin Inc. 3391 Penguin 3, 1996-m-0120-0003; 1 (Box 31)
      - Disk #4 Viking Penguin Inc. 3391 Penguin 4, 1996-m-0120-0004; 1 (Box 31)
      - Disk #5 Viking Penguin Inc. 3391 Penguin 5, 1996-m-0120-0005; 1 (Box 31)
      - Disk #6 Viking Penguin Inc. 3392 Penguin 6, 1996-m-0120-0006; 1 (Box 31)
      - Viking Penguin Inc. 3391 The Artist's Hdbk Appendix Viking - pages 610-638, 1996-m-0120-0007; 1 (Box 31)
    - Fourth revision, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Planning, 1978-1988 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Various articles, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Warehouse drawings - The Case of Paintings, 1940- (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1912-1990
  Scope and Contents
  Includes correspondence to and from Ralph Mayer and Bena Frank Mayer.
  - 1958-1959 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - 1980 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Alkyd, 1985 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Allenby, Edward T., 1962-1984 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Allenby, Edward T., Hilton, and Herb Aach, 1961-1985 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - American Artist
    - 1965-1972 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Answered
      - 1968 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - 1970 (Box 14, Folder 3)
        Includes correspondence about Mayer book.
      - 1970-1971 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - 1971 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - 1972 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - 1973 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - 1974 (Box 14, Folder 8)
        Includes correspondence with Perry Brainer.
      - 1975 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - 1976 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - 1977 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - 1979 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Column, 1978-1979 (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1979 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Not answered
      - 1942-1954 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - 1975-1978 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - 1977 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Queries, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Technical page, 1960-1969 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Unsorted, 1977-1982 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Writing, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - American Association of Museums
    - New Orleans and Washington, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Oberlin, Ohio, 1953-1973 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Philadelphia meeting, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Washington, D. C., 1973 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - American Medical Association, 1965-1968 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Answered by Ralph, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Appendix A, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Acquisition of painting, 1980-1983 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Armco porcelain enameling, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Art Digest, 1945-1954 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Artists Equity Association of New York, 1972-1980 (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Artists' Technical Research Institute correspondence with artists, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Art Students League
    - 1930 (Box 15, Folder 21-22)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Steve, Rosina, Circa 1912-1990 (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - B, 1968-1976 (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Benton, Thomas H., 1952 (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Berger and Bena Mayer, 1969-1980 (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Bressler
    - Court case, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Finances, 1981-1989 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Including "rug" letter (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Lowe, 1981-1983 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - University of Delaware, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Brown, Hilton
    - 1979-1985 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - 1986 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Letter, 1984-05-02 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Stoner, Joyce Hill, 1984-1986 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Burchfield and notes on materials, Circa 1912-1990 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - C, 1969-1977 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Canvas dates, 1960-1965 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Cards, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Chinese book, Ralph Mayer and Maximilian Toch, 1925? (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Columbia
    - Law School, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Paintings, 1957-1960 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Portraits, with photographs, 1961-1964 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Column, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Congratulations regarding center, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Conservation letters, 1932-1941 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Conservation letters and reports, 1937-1959 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Consultations, 1945-1971 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Cornell, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Current letters, 1984-1986 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - D, 1969-1975 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Deutsch Gallery, 1982-1989 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Dictionary, 1951-1971 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Early University of Delaware, 1980-1981 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Eliot, Lucy, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Encyclopedia Americana, 1959-1971 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica
    - 1940-1964 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - 1947 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - 1970 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - P. F. Collier, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Establishment of Artists Technical Research Institute, 1954-1966 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Faber and Faber, 1948-1969 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Faber Technology, 1953-1969 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - G, 1967-1973 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Gettens, R. J., 1953-1970 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Gluck, 1961-1976 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Harper and Row, 1983-1990 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Individuals' letters from 1961 news release on Artists Technical Research Institute, 1961-1970 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Industrial pigments, 1970-1976 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Information on slide lecture, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Interlayer adhesion, miscellaneous projects, 1960-1969 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - International Institute for the Conservation of Historic and Artistic Works (IIC)
    - General, 1939-1972 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - London, 1958-1977 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Personal, 1949-1978 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - K, 1949-1973 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Keepsakes number 2, 1973-1977 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - L, 1946-1969 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Landon, Ed, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Latexture, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Laudatory letters from artists, 1938-1979 (Box 18, Folder 17-18)
  - Lectures: correspondence and materials, 1965-1977 (Box 18, Folder 19)